here are the stories were covering this
evo priča koje su pokrivale ovo
week in the category 5 TV newsroom
tjedna u TV redakciji kategorije 5. \ t
Broadcom has confirmed a 130 billion
Broadcom je potvrdio 130 milijardi
dollar buyout frit offer for their
dolar buyout frit ponuda za svoje
arrival Qualcomm some iPhone users are
Dolazak Qualcomm-a kod nekih iPhone korisnika
fuming over the new letter i bug tour
fuming nad novim slovom i bug tour
has been leaking users real IP addresses
je curenje korisnika stvarne IP adrese
and australia's a multi-million dollar
a Australija je više miliona dolara
broadband network is under attack from
širokopojasne mreže je pod napadom od
cockatoos these stories are coming right
kakadu ove priče dolaze pravo
up don't go anywhere
ne idi nigde
Jeff Weston jela you're building a
Jeff Weston jela koju gradite
brand-new beautiful website what are you
potpuno novi web sajt koji ste vi
you're terrible actor what this is where
ti si strašno glumac šta je ovo, gdje
acting comes into play you're supposed
gluma se pojavljuje u igri
to act okay are you building a really
da se dobro ponašaš, ako stvarno gradiš
cool website are you building a really
cool web stranica koju gradite stvarno
cool website just because Jeff is
cool website samo zato što je Jeff
confused doesn't mean you have to be
zbunjeno ne znači da moraš biti
visit cap five dot TV slash dream host
posjeti cap pet dot TV slash host hostel
to sign up for unlimited web hosting for
da se prijavite za neograničen web hosting za
your website with unlimited email
Vašu web stranicu s neograničenom e-poštom
accounts MySQL databases the latest
račune MySQL baze podataka najnovije
version of PHP WordPress and more and
verziju PHP WordPressa i više i
even a free domain name registration
čak i besplatnu registraciju naziva domena
it's less than six dollars per month so
to je manje od šest dolara mesečno
sign up today cat five dot TV slash
prijavite se danas cat pet dot TV slash
DreamHost
DreamHost
this
ovo
is the category 5 TV newsroom covering
je televizijska redakcija kategorije 5 TV
the week's top tech stories with a
vrhunske tehnološke priče sa sedmicom
slight linux - I'm Sasha Rickman and
small linux - Ja sam Sasha Rickman i
here the top stories were following this
ovde su prateće glavne priče
week
week
Broadcom has confirmed its multi-billion
Broadcom je potvrdio svoju više milijardi
dollar bid for Qualcomm revealing more
ponuda za Qualcomm, otkrivajući više
details of the 130 billion dollar
detalji o 130 milijardi dolara
all-cash and shares offer to buy out its
sve-gotovine i dionica ponuditi da kupi svoje
rival chip maker both Qualcomm and
konkurentski proizvođač čipova i Qualcomm i
Broadcom are specialists in
Broadcom su specijalisti u
system-on-chip products putting arm
sistem-na-čipu stavljanje ruku
compatible silicon into various items
kompatibilan silicij u različite predmete
such as smartphones and the wildly drawn
kao što su pametni telefoni i divlji nacrtani
world of the Internet of Things which
svet interneta stvari koji
all chip makers regard as the future of
svi proizvođači čipova smatraju budućnost
chip sales and manufacture broad coms
prodaja čipova i proizvodnja širokog komada
offer comprises $70 per share which we
ponuda obuhvata 70 dolara po akciji koju mi
now know is a fact and is made up of 60
sada znamo činjenicu i sastoji se od 60
dollars in cash and $10 in stocks
dolara u gotovini i $ 10 u akcijama
Broadcom CFO Thomas Kraus said we look
Finansijski direktor kompanije Broadcom Thomas Kraus je rekao da gledamo
forward to engaging immediately in
odmah se uključiti
discussions with Qualcomm so that we can
razgovore sa Qualcomm-om kako bismo mogli
sign a definitive agreement and
potpisati konačni sporazum i
completes this transaction expeditiously
završava ovu transakciju ekspeditivno
it's a bold move by Broadcom Qualcomm on
to je hrabar potez kompanije Broadcom Qualcomm
the other hand has sued Apple attracted
druga ruka je tužila Apple privlači
the interest of antitrust authorities in
interes antitrustovskih vlasti
America and earned the an enemy of Intel
Amerika je zaradila neprijatelja Intela
on the flip side it's not only
na drugoj strani to nije samo
profitable but is in the middle of its
profitabilan, ali je usred svog
own multi-billion dollar buyout of
sopstvenog otkupa od više milijardi dolara
arrival so the Internet of Things is
dolazak tako da je internet stvari
definitely 100 percent the future of
definitivno 100% budućnosti
this actual product itself right well
ovo samo po sebi pravo i stvarni proizvod
sure yeah the Internet of Things being
sigurno da je Internet stvari bitno
like connected devices and and so on
kao što su povezani uređaji i tako dalje
right so if you're a chip manufacturer
tako da ako ste proizvođač čipova
you want to be in on that right okay so
želite da budete u na to pravo u redu tako
what exactly is a system on a chip like
šta je tačno sistem na čipu
it's well I would imagine I mean we're
mislim da mislim da smo mi
talking about chips with firmwares so
govorimo o čipovima sa firmwares tako
that the software is actually running on
da li je softver zapravo radi na
the circuit on the chip itself but these
krug na samom čipu, ali ovi
guys I mean Broadcom does I think it's
Mislim da je to Broadcom
like broadcast circuits and chips and
kao što su emisioni krugovi i čipovi
Qualcomm does the modems for these
Qualcomm radi modeme za njih
devices so various different you know
Uređaji su tako različiti da znate
different needs you know you think of an
Različite potrebe znate da mislite na
iPhone and you think about a specific
iPhone i vi mislite o određenom
phone you don't think about the fact
telefon ne misliš na činjenicu
that each little chip is made by
da je svaki mali čip napravljen
different
drugačije
Broadcom being one qualcomm being
Broadcom je jedan qualcomm biće
another mm-hmm right exactly but I you
još jedan mm-hmm tačno ali ja
know what my question is if Qualcomm is
znam šta je moje pitanje da li je Qualcomm
doing so well and is actually a good
to je dobro i zapravo je dobro
rival why bother is Qualcomm doing so
suparnik zašto se trudi da Qualcomm to učini
well well they're profitable they say
dobro kažu da su profitabilne
hey seventy bucks a share that's the
hej sedamdeset dolara po dionici to je
offer
ponuda
okay so Qualcomm is profitable right
u redu tako Qualcomm je profitabilan pravo
right consider the dispute that they've
pravo razmotriti spor koji su oni
had since before January with Apple like
još od prije januara sa Apple poput
they're one of their biggest customers
oni su jedan od njihovih najvećih klijenata
and obviously one of the biggest
i očigledno jedan od najvećih
manufacturers in the world as far as
proizvođača u svijetu što se tiče
mobile devices and and that kind of
mobilnih uređaja i i tu vrstu
thing goes so they're profitable yeah
ide tako da su profitabilne da
we're making money we're in the black
zarađujemo novac smo u crnom
but we're not if they're 90 percent down
ali nismo ako su 90% niže
on previous years so their their profit
na prethodne godine, tako da je njihov profit
right is way down compared to previous
desno je niže u poređenju sa prethodnim
years so no they're not doing well
godina tako da ne rade dobro
they're they are profitable they're
oni su profitabilni
still making money but they're on the
i dalje zarađuje, ali oni su na
decline right okay Wow so you know the
odbiti pravo u redu Wow tako da znate
the thing with that you know why would
stvar sa kojom znate zašto bi to učinila
Broadcom be looking at buying Qualcomm
Broadcom traži kupovinu Qualcomma
well it's it's an opportunity they're
to je prilika za njih
doing poorly right now right and as far
rade loše sada pravo i koliko
as that goes and I think it really all
kako to ide i mislim da je to zaista sve
surrounds the Apple thing I shouldn't
okružuje Apple stvar koju ne bih trebao
say that they're doing poorly they're
kažu da rade loše
not then they have other customers but
ne onda oni imaju druge kupce, ali
the whole thing with Apple is they
čitava stvar sa Apple je da oni
they've got patents that they're just
imaju patente da su samo
you know Apple is disputing the fees
znate da Apple osporava takse
that go along with those patents and
koji se slažu s tim patentima i
Qualcomm is fighting them and they're
Qualcomm se bori protiv njih i oni su
suing each other and there's all these
tuže jedni druge i sve to
lawsuits going back and forth right so
tužbe ide nazad u pravu tako
it makes me wonder if there's a
pitam se da li postoji
perspective on it that you know broke up
perspektiva na to što znate raspala
sitting there going well if they win
sedeći tamo ide dobro ako pobede
this we get access to all of you
ovo je pristup za sve vas
earnings if Apple or oh if they win the
zarade ako Apple ili oh ako pobijede
buyer this is it here's the thing so
kupac to je to evo stvar tako
imagine they're their stocks of their
zamislite da su njihove zalihe
stocks went down yep Qualcomm because of
zalihe su se spustile za Qualcomm zbog
the lawsuit and everything else so
tužbu i sve ostalo tako
they're doing poorly that way then along
rade loše na taj način onda zajedno
comes Broadcom in this perfect moment
dolazi Broadcom u ovom savršenom trenutku
and like a vulture says okay we'll give
i kao što lešinar kaže da ćemo u redu
you this unimaginable like the biggest
ti ovaj nezamisliv kao najveći
buyout in tech ever 100 billion dollars
otkup u tehnologiji ikada 100 milijardi dolara
and in order to take over your company
i da biste preuzeli vašu kompaniju
so if they say yes now Broadcom buys up
pa ako kažu da sada, Broadcom kupuje
all those the patent portfolio now owns
sve one koje patentni portfolio sada posjeduje
it and settles the
to i rešava
with Apple fixes that relationship
sa Appleom popravlja taj odnos
because Apple is already on the fence
jer je Apple već na ogradi
about their relationship with Qualcomm
o njihovom odnosu sa Qualcomm-om
and saying you know maybe we want to
i kažete da znate možda želimo
just sever this relationship altogether
samo sever taj odnos potpuno
so if they say yes if Qualcomm says yes
pa ako kažu da ako Qualcomm kaže da
to the buyout now Broadcom can fix
na otkup sada Broadcom može popraviti
things with Apple and and redeem that
stvari s Apple i i otkupiti taj
whole relationship and become this
cijelu vezu i postanite to
bigger entity now if if Qualcomm says no
sada ako je Qualcomm rekao ne
however the stocks go back down the
međutim, akcije se vraćaju
stocks plummet right and Apple says you
dionice padaju dobro i Apple vam kaže
know what we still want out you know now
znate šta još uvek želite da znate
that's not a sure thing this is just a
to nije sigurna stvar, ovo je samo
theory but you know what what timing
teorija, ali znate šta je tajming
what absolute timing if you're Qualcomm
Apsolutno vreme ako ste Qualcomm
you pretty much don't have a choice you
ti uglavnom nemaš izbora
kind of don't I kind of feel that way
nekako se tako ne osjećam
it's like okay we really need to take
to je kao u redu stvarno moramo uzeti
this otherwise we're done yeah
inače smo gotovi
like our stocks are way down now their
kao što su naše zalihe sada niže
stocks rose when they offer came right
dionice su porasle kada su ponudile pravo
like they're like big-time and are
kao da su velike i da su
continuing to rise at a slower pace but
nastavlja da raste sporije no
you know it's it's happening so as soon
znaš da se to događa tako brzo
as they say yes it's gonna be a good
kako kažu da će biti dobro
thing for you know for everything
stvar za koju znate za sve
involved but if they say no then it's
ali ako kažu ne, onda je to
gonna drop right back down yeah exactly
baciti vraćam da upravo
it's all in relation to broad commenting
sve je u vezi sa širokim komentiranjem
Wow thank you well things that happen
Wow hvala vam dobro što se događa
behind the scenes
iza scene
speaking of Apple some iPhone users have
Govoreći o Appleu, neki iPhone korisnici imaju
been left frustrated after an update to
ostao frustriran nakon ažuriranja
the iOS operating system
operativni sistem iOS
curiously began to autocorrect the
radoznalo je počeo da ispravlja
letter I to a capital a with a question
slovo I do glavnog a sa pitanjem
mark the affected version of iOS 11.1 is
Označite pogođenu verziju iOS 11.1
available on iPhones and iPads a
dostupno na iPhones i iPads a
technology reporter shared his
reporter tehnologije podijelio je svoje
frustration on Twitter saying I have a
frustracije na Twitteru govoreći da imam a
one thousand one hundred and fifty
hiljadu sto pedeset
dollar telephone that can't read the
dolarski telefon koji ne može da čita
letter I
slovo I
Apple has outlined a temporary fix for
Apple je izdvojio privremeni popravak za
the problem on its website the fix
problem na njegovoj web stranici
involves editing the keyboard settings
uključuje uređivanje postavki tastature
so enough in iOS so that the right
dovoljno u iOS-u, tako da je pravo
character either an upper or lowercase I
znak ili gornja ili mala slova I
is used Apple has said that the issue
koristi se Apple je rekao da je problem
will be fixed in a future software
će se popraviti u budućem softveru
updates and not all iOS 11.1 users have
ažuriranja, a ne svi korisnici iOS 11.1
been affected Wow the Canadian the
Wow the Canadian the
Canadian it's not a bug it's a Canadian
Kanadski to nije greška, to je kanadski
upgrade you wouldn't think that would be
nadogradnja ne bi pomislila da bi to bilo
a simple patch just fix it upload it and
jednostavno zakrpa samo popraviti to upload i
be done with it in one day
s tim u jednom danu
right right you think you would think
desno misliš da misliš
that but it could perhaps it's it's not
ali to možda nije
I'm kind of envying Android right now
Nekako sam zavidim Android odmah
where if you have problems with your
gde imate problema sa svojim
keyboard you just install a different
tastaturu koju instalirate drugačije
keyboard yeah Apple is like locked in
tastatura Da Apple je kao zaključan
it's like you're on Apple you can't
kao da si na Apple-u, ne možeš
change things so cause an autocorrect
promenite stvari tako da izazovu autokorekciju
issue like that bad dictionary a virus
problem kao što je onaj loš rječnik
not a virus I don't think that'd be
ne virus koji mislim da ne bi bio
pretty unlikely I mean it could be like
prilično teško Mislim da bi mogao biti kao
a disgruntled employee who you know
nezadovoljni zaposlenik koga poznajete
having tried to delete the president's
pokušavajući da izbriše predsednika
Twitter account and so decided to inject
Tviter nalog i tako odlučio da ubrizgate
strange character it sounds to me like
čudan karakter koji mi zvuči
this was an update to iOS 11 point one
ovo je bila nadogradnja za iOS 11 tačku jedan
that was meant to introduce all these
to je trebalo da uvede sve ovo
new emojis so maybe maybe maybe the
novi emojis pa možda možda možda i
emot-- like i think about i and then a
emot-- kao što mislim o i i onda a
stray or a and then a strange question
lutalica ili neko čudno pitanje
mark character this kind of seems to me
Čini mi se da je ovakav znak
like maybe a high ascii issue or
kao možda visoko ascii pitanje ili
something like that so you know the
tako nešto da znate
programmer me thinks maybe the you know
programer mi misli da možda znaš
it's trying to output a unicode
pokušava ispisati unicode
character or something like that so what
karakter ili nešto slično pa šta
that means is maybe it was just that key
to znači da je možda samo taj ključ
that particular autocorrect got
da je određeni autokorent dobio
corrupted or changed to something that
korumpiran ili promijenjen u nešto to
it shouldn't have been and so it's
to nije trebalo da bude i tako je
correcting everything because as you
ispravlja sve zato što kao ti
type it replaces words so imagine every
tip zamjenjuje riječi tako zamislite svaki
time you press I and hit space it
kada pritisnete ja i pritisnete ga
replaces it with a should be fine unless
zamenjuje ga sa treba da bude dobro osim ako
you're trying to type in your password
pokušavate da unesete lozinku
[Laughter]
[Smeh]
maybe it seems a little bit too good to
možda se čini da je to malo previše dobro
be true is very humor Macs and Linux
biti istinito je vrlo humor Mac i Linux
versions of the Tor anonymity browser
verzije pretraživača za anonimnost Tor
just received a temporary fix for
samo za privremeni popravak
critical vulnerability that leaks users
kritična ranjivost koja propušta korisnike
IP addresses whenever they visit certain
IP adrese kad god posjete određene
types of addresses turmoil as the flaw
vrste adresa su previranja kao mana
has been dubbed by its Discoverer is
je nazvan po svojoj Discoverer je
triggered when users click on links that
pokreću se kada korisnici kliknu na veze koje
begin with file colon slash slash rather
početi sa datoteku debelog crijeva slash slash radije
rather than the more common HTTP colon
radije nego češće HTTP debelo crijevo
slash slash and HTTP
kosa crta i HTTP
pe : / / address prefixes when the tor
pe: / / adresni prefiksi kada je tor
browser for Mac OS and Linux is in the
pretraživač za Mac OS i Linux je u
process of opening such an address the
proces otvaranja takve adrese
operating system may directly connect to
operativni sistem se može direktno povezati
the remote host by bypassing tor browser
udaljenog hosta zaobilazeći browser
on Friday members of the Tor project in
u petak članovi Tor projekta u
issued a temporary workaround that plugs
izdao je privremeno rješenje koje uključuje čepove
the IP leak until the final fixes in
curenje IP-a do konačnih popravaka
place updated versions of the browser
postavite ažurirane verzije pretraživača
may not behave properly when navigating
možda se ne ponaša ispravno prilikom navigacije
to file : / / addresses they said both
u datoteku: / / adrese su rekle oboje
the windows versions of tor and tails as
verzije prozora tor i tails kao
well as the sandboxed tor browser that's
kao i sanduk u torzeru koji je
in alpha testing aren't vulnerable
u alfa testiranju nisu ranjive
tor statement Friday said that there's
izjava tor petak je rekao da postoji
no evidence that the flaw has been
nema dokaza da je greška bila
actively exploited on the Internet or
aktivno se koristi na internetu ili
dark web to obtain the IP addresses of
tamno web dobiti IP adrese
tor users of course the lack of evidence
naravno, nedostatak dokaza
doesn't mean that the flaw wasn't
ne znači da greška nije
exploited by law enforcement officers
koriste službenici za sprovođenje zakona
private investigators or even stalkers
privatni istražitelji ili čak stalkeri
for that matter and now that a fix is
za tu stvar i sada kada je popravak
available it will be easy for advert
na raspolaganju će biti lako za oglas
adversaries who don't know about the
protivnici koji ne znaju za
vulnerability before to create working
ranjivost prije stvaranja rada
exploits anyone who relies on Mac or
eksploatiše svakoga ko se oslanja na Mac ili Mac
Linux versions of the tor browser to
Linux verzije tor preglednika u
shield their IP address should update as
štit njihove IP adrese treba ažurirati kao
soon as possible and be ready for the
najkraćem mogućem roku i biti spreman za
possibility however remote that their IP
međutim, moguća je njihova IP
addresses have already been leaked hmm
adrese već su procurili hmm
Wow very tool that's meant to protect
Wow vrlo alat koji je namijenjen za zaštitu
your IP and identity yeah boys I have
Vaš IP i identitet da momci imam
used and understand the prefix HTTPS
koristi i razume prefiks HTTPS
right would you an HTTP much a secure
da li bi HTTP bio siguran
website exactly unsecured website I've
website točno neosigurana web stranica sam
never typed in file colon slash slash
nikada nije ukucao u datoteku kolona kosu crtu
well you could click on links on a
dobro možete kliknuti na linkove na a
website that would take you there right
website koji će vas odvesti tamo pravo
of course but like I don't understand
naravno, ali kao da ne razumem
why you would even need to use something
zašto biste uopšte morali nešto da koristite
like that like what's the okay so file
kao što je to što je u redu, onda fajl
colon slash slash typically refers to
kolona crta kosa crta tipično se odnosi na
files on your own hard drive so a
datoteke na vašem hard disku tako da
website for example if I was creating a
na primjer, ako sam kreirao
tutorial on how to access Network shares
tutorial o tome kako pristupiti mrežnim dijelovima
I could tell you in my tutorial on my
Mogao bih da vam kažem u svom tutorialu na mom
blog
blog
in order to access your server at IP
kako bi pristupili vašem serveru na IP
address 192.168.0.1 i 2.16 a done so i
adresa 192.168.0.1 i 2.16 je učinio i
could use it in a tutorial and file
mogao bi ga koristiti u udžbeniku i datoteci
colon slash slash tells my browser do
debelog crijeva slash slash govori moje preglednika uraditi
this on the local network or it might be
ovo na lokalnoj mreži ili može biti
like a local file for some you know for
kao lokalni fajl za neke koje poznajete
some reason or you know a local uploaded
iz nekog razloga ili znate lokalnog postavljenog
image or something so there are cases
slika ili nešto tako da postoje slučajevi
where it could be needed or where it is
gdje bi to moglo biti potrebno ili gdje je
legitimately used I know like doc you
legitimno korišćen Ja znam kao doktor
week II for example will convert local
tjedan II, na primjer, pretvorit će lokalne
network share addresses into links so
mreže dijele adrese u veze tako
that if I'm on my personal network and I
da ako sam na svojoj ličnoj mreži i ja
click on that link it will take me to my
kliknite na link koji će me odvesti do mog
local internal server so that's a file
lokalni interni server tako da je to datoteka
colon slash slash link fairly uncommon
kolona slash slash veza prilično neuobičajena
but in the you know in the wild once
ali u jednom znate u divljini
this exploit is now known people may in
ovaj podvig je sada poznat ljudima može u
fact put those links on websites or not
Činjenica staviti te linkove na web stranice ili ne
even links but JavaScript redirects for
čak i veze, ali za JavaScript preusmjeravanja
example to exploit the person's IP
na primer da bi se iskoristila IP osoba
address yeah now that the fix is
sada se obratite da je popravak
available now people are like you know
sada su ljudi kao što znate
what happens when a fix comes out is
šta se dešava kada se otkrije popravak je
everybody who is malicious says oh
svako ko je zlonameran kaže oh
that's how I can get people people's IP
tako mogu da dobijem IP ljudi
addresses right now there's a fix I know
adresama sada postoji fix znam
how to exploit that browser know for
kako iskoristiti taj pretraživač znam
people they use tor browser they
ljudi koje koriste u browseru
obviously don't want their IP addresses
očigledno ne žele njihove IP adrese
to be exposed so what happens in this
da bude izložen pa šta se dešava u ovome
case now where their IP address is
sada kada je njihova IP adresa
exposed is there anything they can do
izloženo je bilo šta što mogu učiniti
what can you do if your IP is exposed
šta možete učiniti ako je vaš IP izložen
right like your isp your internet
baš kao i vaš internet
service provider controls your IP
provajder servisa kontroliše vaš IP
address think of the IP as and it stands
obratite se na IP kao i on stoji
for Internet Protocol it's your your
za Internet protokol je vaš
your phone number for your computer
broj telefona za vaš računar
right your network so when you go to
ispravite mrežu tako da idete
Google and you type in a search it
Google i upišete u pretragu ga
responds back to your computer with the
se vraća vašem računaru sa
results and that is done through your IP
rezultate i to je učinjeno kroz vaš IP
address and that's very very important
i to je veoma važno
and it generally you know if you're on
i općenito znate da li ste uključeni
cable or there fiber or anything like
kabl ili vlakno ili nešto slično
that
to
generally doesn't change and if it does
generalno se ne menja i ako jeste
is very infrequent like every couple of
veoma je rijedak kao i svaki par
years
godina
I know cable cable internet here in
Znam kablovski kablovski internet ovde
Canada it might be every couple years
Kanada može biti svakih par godina
you'll see your IP address changed when
videćete da je vaša IP adresa promenjena kada
they rolled out ipv6 the IP address is
izašli su ipv6 IP adresa je
change
promena
and I think that's the only time that
i mislim da je to jedini put
I've had a change in four years let's
Imao sam promjenu u četiri godine idemo
see with mine if I restart my modem
vidi sa mojim ako ponovo pokrenem svoj modem
mm-hmm my IP address changes so you're
mm-hmm moja IP adresa se mijenja tako da ste vi
on DSL no I'm on cable you're on cable
na DSL-u nema na kablu
and are you sure it changes your policy
i jeste li sigurni da to menja vašu politiku
changes yep
promjene yep
so some ISPs do that yeah because
tako da neki ISP-ovi to rade zato
there's a pool of IP addresses there's
tamo je bazen IP adresa
no guarantee that it's going to change
nema garancije da će to promijeniti
when you restart your router no
kada ponovo pokrenete ruter br
certainly DSL is a case where it's
sigurno je DSL slučaj u kome je
probably going to change because it it
verovatno će se promeniti zato što je to
reconnects over pppoe with your username
ponovo se povezuje preko pppoea sa vašim korisničkim imenom
and password and then gets a new IP
i lozinku, a zatim dobija novi IP
address right every time you restart
obratiti pravo svaki put kada ponovo
your router or your modem so it's a
ruter ili modem tako da je to
little bit different but with internet
malo drugačije, ali sa internetom
on cable it quite often it keeps the
na kablu često ga zadržava
same IP address and that's what shocked
Ista IP adresa i to je ono što je šokiralo
me is when I saw that mine reset I was
ja sam kad sam vidio da sam bio resetiran
like yeah that's interesting because I
kao da, to je interesantno, jer ja
shot it with my ISP about it and I'm
Snimao sam ga sa svojim ISP-om o tome i ja sam
like why did this happen it's a security
kao što se to dogodilo, to je sigurnost
feature they have in a business though
ipak imaju u poslovanju
in a business typically you're gonna be
u poslu obično ćete biti
sitting on a static IP a correct yes
sedeći na statičkoj IP ispravno da
that means that phone number of your
to znači taj broj telefona
network never changes so if somebody is
mreža se nikada ne mijenja tako da je netko
exploited on that IP address you are
eksploatisani na toj IP adresi koju jeste
never going to lose that IP address it
nikada neće izgubiti tu IP adresu
is now identifiable to you good types if
sada vam je moguće prepoznati dobre vrste ako
you're interested in knowing what an IP
Zainteresovani ste da znate šta je IP
address reveals here's a little trick
adresa otkriva ovde je mali trik
for you go to Google okay so just go to
za vas idite na Google u redu pa samo idite na
your favorite Google search engine and
vaš omiljeni Google pretraživač i
the reason I say Google is because they
razlog zašto kažem Google je zato što oni
have a tool in the search instead of
imati alat u pretrazi umjesto
doing a search just type in IP so that
obavljajući pretragu samo upišite IP tako da
stands for Internet Protocol and it will
stoji za Internet Protocol i to će
actually respond with your public IP
u stvari odgovoriti vašim javnim IP-om
address so what Google sees your IP
adresa tako da Google vidi vaš IP
address is now copy that and go to Mac's
adresa je sada kopirajte i idite na Mac
mind comm ma X M IND com Mac's mind is a
mind comm ma XM IND com Mac-ov um je
geolocation technology that allows
tehnologija geolokacije koja to omogućava
credit-card processors and banks and
procesore kreditnih kartica i banke i
online sales portals to use IP
online prodajni portali za upotrebu IP-a
geolocation data to verify people's
geolokacioni podaci za verifikaciju ljudi
identities so that service is used for
identiteta kako bi se usluga koristila
legitimate purposes so that people can
legitimne svrhe tako da ljudi mogu
verify that
potvrdite to
hey yeah you're making a purchase on my
hej da kupujete na mom računu
website you're you say you're from
web-mjesto za koje ste rekli da ste
Quebec and indeed you are check if you
Quebec i zaista ste provjerili da li ste
say you're from Quebec and you're
kažete da ste iz Quebeca i da ste
actually in Israel I think there's a red
zapravo u Izraelu mislim da je crveno
flag there so you go to max my comm and
zastavicu tamo tako da idete na max moj comm i
if you scroll down the page a little bit
ako spustimo stranicu malo
there's a little place where you can
postoji malo mesto gde možete
paste an IP
zalijepite IP
to test it paste that IP address from
da testirate paste sa te IP adrese
Google in there and go and you're gonna
Idi tamo i idi i ti ćeš
see all the information that Mack's mind
vidjeti sve informacije koje Mack um
reveals about your IP address Oh
otkriva o vašoj IP adresi Oh
interesting little test for you if you'd
zanimljiv mali test za vas
like to see what your IP address reveals
volite da vidite šta vam otkriva IP adresa
I'm doing that today very very cool
Radim to danas vrlo kul
thank you take it one step further real
hvala ti ga uzeti jedan korak dalje u realnom
quick it gives you a longitude and
brzo vam daje dužinu i
latitude copy that paste it back into
širine kopija da zalijepite ga natrag u
Google Maps it tells you where you are
Google Maps vam govori gdje se nalazite
nope just try it okay gives you a
ne, samo pokušajte, dobro je
longitude and latitude result paste it
dužina i širina rezultat zalijepite
into Google Maps and see what you find
u Google mape i vidite šta ste pronašli
I'm actually scared all right
Ja sam zapravo uplašio sve u redu
Australia's a multi-million dollar
Australija je više miliona dolara
broadband network is under attack from
širokopojasne mreže je pod napadom od
cockatoos the national broadcast network
kakadu u nacionalnoj mreži emitovanja
said it has spent tens of thousands of
rekao je da je potrošio desetine hiljada
dollars so far fixing cables that have
dolara do sada fiksiranje kablova koji imaju
been chewed by the birds they also
Žvakale su i ptice
estimate the bill will rise sharply as
procjena će naglo porasti
more damage is uncovered in an attempts
u pokušaju je otkriveno više štete
to improve Australia's internet speed
za poboljšanje brzine interneta u Australiji
currently lagging behind many developed
trenutno zaostaje za mnogim razvijenim
countries 11.1 megabits per second a
zemlje 11.1 megabita u sekundi a
national telecommunications
nacionalne telekomunikacije
infrastructure project has been
infrastrukturni projekat
instigated and is due for completion in
podstaknut i treba da bude završen
but engineers have engineers returning
ali inženjeri imaju inženjere koji se vraćaju
to sites have been finding spare cables
na sajtove su pronašli rezervne kablove
chewed and frayed the culprits are
žvakali i izlizali krivce
cockatoos a type of parrot which
kakadu vrsta papiga koji
normally eats fruit nuts wood and bark
normalno jede voće i drvo kore
and now wires the company has had to
i sada žice koje je kompanija morala
replace power and fiber cables at the
zamijeniti strujne i optičke kablove na
cost of tens of thousands of dollars
košta desetine hiljada dolara
each time so far they say they have
svaki put do sada kažu da imaju
spent $80,000 of local currency which is
potrošio $ 80,000 u lokalnoj valuti koja je
roughly sixty one thousand five hundred
otprilike šezdeset tisuća pet stotina
u.s. the company says it's currently
nama kompanija kaže da je trenutno
installing perfected perspective casings
instaliranje usavršenih kućišta perspektive
which cost $14 each and that will
koji koštaju po 14 dolara i to hoće
protect the wires from the birds in the
štiti žice od ptice u
future and save billions of dollars and
budućnosti i uštedite milijarde dolara i
saved their 3 billion dollar Network for
spasio svoju mrežu 3 milijarde dolara za
further damage stop making the Internet
dalje štete prestaju da stvaraju internet
out of nuts and berries it reminds me of
od oraha i bobica to me podsjeća na
an old story that we told in the news
stara priča da smo rekli u vijestima
about mice were eating the in
o miševi su jeli je u
like the soundproofing or something
kao zvučna izolacija ili nešto slično
inside a car that was oh yes yes right
u automobilu koji je bio oh da da pravo
they had some kind of biodegradable
imali su neku vrstu biorazgradivog
insulation
izolacija
yeah and wiring the traction that was
Da i ožičenje je bilo
apparently delicious so I'm thinking
očigledno ukusna pa mislim
that the birds probably aren't eating
da ptice verovatno ne jedu
the wires I think that they're probably
Žice mislim da su verovatno
using them as as either nest material
koristeći ih kao materijal za gnezdo
because it probably looks like a twig or
jer verovatno izgleda kao grančica ili
perhaps Australia didn't think about it
možda Australija nije razmišljala o tome
and put something yummy in there you
i staviti nešto ukusan u tu si
know what I think it's more that they're
znam šta mislim da je više od njih
sharpening their beaks I mean they're no
Mislim da nisu
yes cockatoos are known to pack a sharp
Da, poznato je da se paketići oštri
sharpen their beak so you get something
izoštri kljun tako da dobiješ nešto
like a good solid wire and looks like a
kao dobra pune žice i izgleda kao
good thing to sharpen that beat guy I
dobra stvar da izoštri da ritam Muškarac
mean as weird as this story is that it's
znači čudno kao što je ova priča da je
cockatoos yeah what I was actually most
kakadu, što sam zapravo najviše
shocked about is the fact that their
šokirana je činjenica da je njihova
internet is so slow oh 11.1 megabits per
internet je tako sporo oh 11,1 megabita po
second and that's high like their
drugi i to je visoko kao njihov
average in Australia is 8.5 like that's
prosjek u Australiji je 8.5 kao da je to
insane how was it that it really is so
ludo kako je bilo da je to zaista tako
far behind on that oh how far behind are
daleko iza tog oh koliko daleko su
they well think about this ultra HD
oni dobro misle o ovoj ultra HD tehnologiji
video on Netflix is 25 megabits per
video na Netflix je 25 megabita po
second alright so why are they so far
U redu, pa zašto su tako daleko
behind Jeff cockatoos no I think you
iza Jeffa kakadua ne mislim da ste vi
know it's probably political the the the
znam da je verovatno politički
company that runs the internet service
kompanija koja vodi internet uslugu
in Australia is government-run and in
u Australiji se vodi i vlada
you know the early 2000s the plan was to
znate početkom 2000-ih plan je bio
upgrade the infrastructure to fibre
nadograditi infrastrukturu na vlakna
we're gonna do 100 megabit fiber lines
napravićemo 100 megabitnih vlakana
all throughout Australia and upgrade
širom Australije i nadogradnju
every one so you know I think the plan
svatko tako da znate da mislim plan
was that 95% of Australia would have
95% Australije
access to fiber Internet that was the
pristup vlakana internetu da je to bio
plan now the 2013 election happened and
plan sada se dogodio izbor za 2013. i
the Liberals came in and said you know
Liberali su došli i rekli da znate
what we're actually gonna change things
šta ćemo zapravo promijeniti
and we're going to instead we're gonna
i mi ćemo umesto toga
focus on cost savings we're gonna try to
fokusirati na smanjenje troškova ćemo pokušati
make you know we're gonna make the black
da znaš da ćemo napraviti crnac
here and that didn't go so well for the
ovdje i da nije išao tako dobro za
Internet no no the choice was made at
Internet nema, izbor je napravljen na
that time that instead of upgrading to
to vreme umesto nadogradnje
fiber we're gonna tap into the existing
vlakna ćemo iskoristiti postojeće
copper infrastructure and try to work
bakrena infrastruktura i pokušati raditi
with that so use newer technologies over
s tim da koriste nove tehnologije preko
the
the
proper infrastructure and keep going
odgovarajuću infrastrukturu i nastavite dalje
with that and so the the idea was that
s tim i tako je ideja bila
it was supposed to be cheaper it was
to je trebalo da bude jeftiniji je to bilo
supposed to be faster to deploy and it
trebalo bi da se brže primeni i to
turned out it was neither and it's
ispostavilo se da to nije bilo i to je
costing them a lot of money and they've
koštalo ih je mnogo novca i oni su
got this terrible infrastructure that is
ima tu užasnu infrastrukturu koja je
being eaten by cockatoos that's too bad
jede ga kakadu, što je previše loše
you're tapping into your sector I think
Mislim da ste prisluškivali svoj sektor
that the solution would be it's
da bi rešenje bilo
government stuff right like so it's like
vladine stvari kao da je tako
a government monopoly over the internet
vlada monopol preko interneta
so imagine if your internet service was
zamislite da li je vaš internet servis
provided by the government that's how it
koje je vlada tako je to
is in Australia so because of that
je zbog toga u Australiji
infrastructure is completely driven by
infrastruktura je u potpunosti vođen
governmental budgets and and legislation
vladinim budžetima i zakonodavstvom
and and bureaucracy so you think about
i i birokratija o kojoj razmišljate
that and you know if they would just
to i vi znate da li bi samo
privatize that sector of you know the
privatizirajte taj sektor od vas
infrastructure of Internet
infrastruktura Interneta
telecommunications if they could
telekomunikacija kad bi mogli
privatized that everywhere cried well
privatizovan da je svuda dobro plakao
I've got a different perspective I'm
Imam drugačiju perspektivu
sure but you think about that you know
naravno, ali vi mislite o tome
why are they so slow that's the question
zašto su tako spori to je pitanje
yeah why is their internet so slow
Da, zašto je njihov internet tako spor
because it's it's not per me it's it's
jer to nije po meni to je to
not publicly right you know it's private
ne javno, znate da je privatno
right now I wanted to you know I think
sada sam htio da znate da mislim
that sorry it should be public because
žao mi je što bi to trebalo biti javno jer
it was public then we've got competition
bila je javna, onda imamo konkurenciju
we've got fair competition we've got the
imamo poštenu konkurenciju koju imamo
price coming down you know the
cijena pada dolje znate
government says oh well the Australians
vlada kaže: "Pa dobro, Australci."
don't want it to be faster we don't want
ne želim da bude brže ne želimo
these that's what they say that's what
to je ono što oni kažu da je ono što
the CEO of the the broad broadcast
generalni direktor široke emitiranja
company or whatever they call themselves
kompanija ili šta god oni sami nazivaju
that's what they said but the fact
to je ono što su rekli, ali činjenica
Achilles they don't want to pay for it
Ahile ne žele da plate za to
you're watching and you're from
gledate, a ti si od
Australia yeah please call me am i right
Australija, molim vas nazovite me da sam u pravu
like it's not I mean the government is
kao da ne mislim na vladu
misquoting Australians and saying that
pogrešno citiranje Australaca i to
they don't want to have it when really
oni to ne žele da imaju
they just don't want to pay the
oni jednostavno ne žele da plate
astronomical fee that the government
astronomska naknada koju plaća vlada
wants to charge them for it so if it was
želi da ih naplati za to , ako jeste
public instead of privatized pardon me
javno, umesto da me privatizuje, pomilujem
if it was public then there'd be
ako je bila javna onda bi bilo
competition and the infrastructure could
konkurencija i infrastruktura
go up and the cost could come down so
idite gore i cena bi mogla da padne tako
now I can get faster internet and it's
sada mogu dobiti brži internet i to je
affordable that's the key thing so
pristupačne to je ključna stvar tako
really the tagline out of this is Polly
Stvarno je riječ o Polly
want a cookie
želim kolačić
for the birds boy oh just bad it's very
za pticu, dečko, oh, samo loše
punny what are you talking about big
punny što pričaš o velikom
thanks to Roy W Nash in our community of
hvala Roy W Nash u našoj zajednici
yours for submitting surveys to us this
vaš za podnošenje anketa nama
week thanks for watching the
sedmica hvala za gledanje
category-five TV newsroom don't forget
TV-redak petih kategorija ne zaboravite
to Like and subscribe for all your tech
da se volite i pretplatite na sve vaše tehnologije
news with a slight Linux bias and for
vijesti sa blagim Linux pristranosti i za
more free content be sure to check out
više besplatnog sadržaja obavezno provjerite
our web site from the category-five TV
naše web stranice iz kategorije pet TV
newsroom I'm Sasha Rickman
redakcija Ja sam Sasha Rickman
[Music]
[Music] \ t
[Applause]
[Aplauz]